<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v5 rel. 3 U (http://www.xmlspy.com)
     by Daniel M Kohn (private) -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-lsr-ospf-prefix-originator-05"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="OSPF Prefix Originator">OSPF Prefix Originator
    Extension</title>

    <author fullname="Aijun Wang" initials="A" surname="Wang">
      <organization>China Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Beiqijia Town, Changping District</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>102209</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>wangaj3@chinatelecom.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Acee Lindem" initials="A" surname="Lindem">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>301 Midenhall Way</street>

          <city>Cary</city>

          <region>NC</region>

          <code>27513</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>acee@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jie Dong" initials="J" surname="Dong">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jie.dong@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Peter Psenak" initials="P" surname="Psenak">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Pribinova Street 10</street>

          <city>Bratislava</city>

          <region>Eurovea Centre, Central 3</region>

          <code>81109</code>

          <country>Slovakia</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>ppsenak@cisco.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ketan Talaulikar" initials="K" surname="Talaulikar">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>S.No. 154/6, Phase I, Hinjawadi</street>

          <city>Pune</city>

          <region/>

          <code>411 057</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ketant@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="19" month="November"/>

    <area>RTG Area</area>

    <workgroup>LSR Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>RFC</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines Open Shortest Path First (OSPF) encodings to
      advertise the router-id of the originator of inter-area prefixes for
      OSPFv2 and OSPFv3 Link-State Advertisements (LSAs). The source
      originator is needed in several multi-area OSPF use cases.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="section-1" title="Introduction">
      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-ospf-mpls-elc"/> defines mechanisms to
      advertise Entropy Readable Label Depth (ERLD) for ingress Label
      Switching Routers (LSR) to discover other LSR's capability of performing
      Entropy Label based load-balancing in MPLS networks. The ingress LSR can
      use this information to construct the appropriate label stack for
      specific traffic requirements, especially in segment routed networks and
      other deployments requiring stacked LSPs.</t>

      <t>However, in inter-area scenarios, the Area Border Router (ABR) does
      not advertise the originating OSPF router-id for inter-area prefixes. An
      OSPF router in one area doesn't know the origin area of inter-area
      prefixes and can't determine the router that originated these prefixes
      or the ERLD capabilities of the destination. Therefore, it is necessary
      to advertise the originator of these inter-area prefixes to ensure the
      ingress LSR can construct the appropriate label stack.</t>

      <t>More generally, <xref target="RFC8476"/> defines a mechanism to
      advertise multiple types of supported Maximum SID Depths (MSD) at node
      and/or link granularity. This information will be referred when the
      head-end router starts to send traffic to destination prefixes. In
      inter-area scenario, it is also necessary for the sender to learn the
      capabilities of the receivers associated with the inter-area
      prefixes.</t>

      <t>There is another scenario where knowing the originator of inter-area
      prefixes is useful. For example, Border Gateway Protocol Link-State
      (BGP-LS) <xref target="RFC7752"/> describes mechanisms using the BGP
      protocol to advertise Link-State information. This information can
      enable a Software Definition Network (SDN) controller to automatically
      determine the underlay network topology.</t>

      <t>However, if the underlay network is partitioned into multiple areas
      and running the OSPF protocol, it is not easy for the SDN controller to
      rebuild the multi-area topology since ABR that connects multiple areas
      will normally hide the detailed topology for these non-backbone areas.
      If only the internal routers within backbone area run the BGP-LS
      protocol, they just learn and report the summary network information
      from the non-backbone areas. If the SDN controller can learn the
      originator of the inter-area prefixes, it is possible to rebuild the
      inter-area topology.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC7794"/> introduces the Intermediate System to
      Intermediate System (IS-IS) "IPv4/IPv6 Source Router IDs"
      Type-Length-Value (TLV) to advertise the source of prefixes leaked from
      a different IS-IS level. This TLV can be used in the above scenarios.
      Such solution can also be applied in networks that run the OSPF
      protocol, but existing OSPF LSAs TLVs must be extended to include the
      router originating the prefix.</t>

      <t>This draft provides such solution for the OSPFv2 <xref target="RFC2328">
      and OSPFv3 <xref target="RFC5340"/> protocols.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Conventions used in this document">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when,
      they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>The following terms are used in this document:<list style="symbols">
          <t>ABR: Area Border Router</t>

          <t>ASBR: Autonomous System Border Router</t>

          <t>ERLD: Entropy Readable Label Depth</t>

          <t>EL: Entropy Label</t>

          <t>IS-IS: Intermediate System to Intermediate System</t>

          <t>LSA: Link-State Advertisement</t>

          <t>MSD: Maximum SID Depths</t>

          <t>NLRI: Network Layer Reachability Information</t>

          <t>OSPF: Open Shortest Path First</t>

          <t>SID: Segment IDentifier</t>

          <t>SDN: Software Definition Network</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="section-4"
             title="Inter-Area Prefix Source Advertisement Use Cases">
      <t>Figure 1 illustrates a topology where OSPF is running in multiple
      areas. R0-R4 are routers in the backbone area, S1-S4 are internal
      routers in area 1, and T1-T4 are internal routers in area 2. R1 and R3
      are ABRs between area 0 and area 1. R2 and R4 are ABRs between area 0
      and area 2. N1 is the network between router S1 and S2 and N2 is the
      network between router T1 and T2. Ls1 is the loopback address of Node S1
      and Lt1 is the loopback address of Node T1.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
                     +-----------------+
                     |IP SDN Controller|
                     +--------+--------+
                              |
                              | BGP-LS
                              |
 +---------------------+------+--------+-----+--------------+
 | +--+        +--+   ++-+   ++-+    +-++   + -+        +--+|
 | |S1+--------+S2+---+R1+---|R0+----+R2+---+T1+--------+T2||
 | +-++   N1   +-++   ++-+   +--+    +-++   ++++   N2   +-++|
 |   |           |     |               |     ||           | |
 |   |           |     |               |     ||           | |
 | +-++        +-++   ++-+           +-++   ++++        +-++|
 | |S4+--------+S3+---+R3+-----------+R4+---+T3+--------+T4||
 | +--+        +--+   ++-+           +-++   ++-+        +--+|
 |                     |               |                    |
 |                     |               |                    |
 |         Area 1      |     Area 0    |      Area 2        |
 +---------------------+---------------+--------------------+

       Figure 1: OSPF Inter-Area Prefix Originator Scenario
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>If S1 wants to send traffic to prefix Lt1 that is connected to T1 in
      another area, it should know the ERLD and MSD values associated with the
      node T1, and then construct the right label stack at the ingress node
      for traffic destined to prefix Lt1.</t>

      <t>In another scenario, If R0 has some method to learn the originator of
      network N1 and reports such information to IP SDN controller, then it is
      possible for the controller to reconstruct the topology in the
      non-backbone areas. The topology reconstruction process and its
      limitations are described in the <xref target="Appendix-A"/> and <xref
      target="Appendix-B"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="External Prefix Source Advertisement Use Cases">
      <t>Figure 2 illustrates a topology where OSPF is running in different
      domain that is connected by an Autonomous System Border Router (ASBR). A,
      B, and C are routers in the Domain 1; C, D, and E are routers in Domain 2.
      Router C is the ASBR between the two domains.</t>

      <t>When router E receives an external prefix, it will redistribute it
      as an AS-External LSA within domain 2. When C receives such LSA, the
      originator information for such external prefix will be lost when it
      encodes the prefix information with the current LSA format field. In some
      situations, it will be helpful if C can advertise such originator
      information.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
+-------------------------------------------------------------------+
|                              |                    External Prefix |
| +---+       +---+          +---+         +---+         +-|-+      |
| | A +-------+ B +----------| C +---------+ D +---------+ E |------|
| +---+       +---+          +---+         +---+         +---+      |
|        Domain 1              |                 Domain 2           |
+-------------------------------------------------------------------+

       Figure 2: OSPF External Prefix Originator Scenario
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>From the above scenarios, we can conclude that it is useful to define
      the OSPF prefix originator sub TLV .</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="section-6" title="Prefix Source Router-ID sub-TLV">
      <t><xref target="RFC7684"/> and <xref target="RFC8362"/> respectively
      define TLV-based LSAs for OSPFv2 and OSPFv3. These documents facilitate
      addition of new attributes for prefixes and provide the basis for a
      sub-TLV to advertise the "Prefix Source Router ID". For OSPFv2, this
      sub-TLV is a sub-TLV of OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV which SHOULD be
      included in the "OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSA" <xref
      target="RFC7684"/> for inter-area prefixes. For OSPFv3, this sub-TLV is
      a sub-TLV of "Inter-Area-Prefix TLV", which SHOULD be included in the
      "E-Inter-Area-Prefix-LSA" <xref target="RFC8362"/>.</t>

      <t>The "Prefix Source Router-ID" sub-TLV has the following format:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |               Type            |              Length           |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |                Prefix Source Router-ID                        |
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
        Figure 3: Prefix Source Router-ID sub-TLV Format
   ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Source Router-ID Sub-TLV Type: 4 (IANA TEMPORARY allocation)
          <xref target="RFC7684"/> or 27 (IANA TEMPORARY allocation) <xref
          target="RFC8362"/></t>

          <t>Length: 4</t>

          <t>Value: Router-ID of OSPFv2/OSPFv3 router that is the source of
          the prefix.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This sub-TLV provides the same functionality as the IS-IS "IPv4/IPv6
      Source Router" TLV defined in <xref target="RFC7794"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Elements of Procedure">
      <t>The following sections describe the procedure to include the newly
      defined "Source Router-ID Sub-TLV" in the related LSA for inter-area
      prefixes and external prefixes respectively.</t>

      <section title="Inter-Area Prefixes">
        <t>When an ABR, for example R2 in Figure 1, receives a Router-LSA
        advertisement in area 2, it SHOULD originate the corresponding "OSPFv2
        Extended Prefix Opaque LSA" for OSPFv2 or "E-Inter-Area-Prefix-LSA"
        for OSPFv3 that includes the Source Router-ID sub-TLV for the network
        prefixes. For example, to identify the source router prefix Lt1 and
        other inter-area prefixes in Figure 1.</t>

        <t>When a router in another area, e.g., S1, receives such LSA, it then
        can ascertain that prefix Lt1 is associated with node T1 and obtain
        the ERLD or MSD value from T1's Router-Information LSA <xref
        target="RFC7770"/> and construct the right label stack at the ingress
        node S1 for traffic destined to prefix Lt1.</t>

        <t>When a router in another area, e.g., R0, receives such LSA, it
        learns the Prefix Source Router-id and includes it in the prefix
        information advertised to an SDN controller as described in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-ls-segment-routing-ext"/>. The SDN controller
        can then use such information to build the inter-area topology
        according to the process described in the <xref target="Appendix-A"/>.
        The topology retrieval process may not suitable for some environments
        as stated in <xref target="Appendix-B"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="External Prefixes">
        <t>When an ASBR, for example C in Figure 2, receives an AS-External LSA for
        an external prefix in domain 2, it SHOULD extract the
        originator information from the "Advertising Router" field from the LSA
        header. When the prefix is advertised into domain 1 as an AS-External LSA,
        router C may also advertise the Source Router-ID using a AS-scoped OSPFv2
        Extended Prefix Opaque LSA or as a Sub-TLV in the OSPFv3 AS-External LSA.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Since this document extends the "OSPFv2 Extended Prefix LSA" and
      "OSPFv3 E-Inter-Area-Prefix LSA", the security considerations for <xref
      target="RFC7684"/> and <xref target="RFC8362"/> are applicable.</t>

      <t>Modification of the "Prefix Source Sub-TLV" could be used for a
      Denial-of-Service attack and could inhibit the use cases described in
      <xref target="section-4"/>. If the OSPF domain is vulnerable to such
      attacks, OSPF authentication should be used as defined for OSPFv2 in
      <xref target="RFC5709"/> and <xref target="RFC7474"/> and for OSPFv3 in
      <xref target="RFC7166"/>.</t>

      <t>Additionally, advertisement of the prefix source for inter-area
      prefixes facilitates reconstruction of the OSPF topology for other
      areas. Network operators may consider their topologies to be sensitive
      confidential data. For OSPFv3, IPsec can be used to provide
      confidentiality <xref target="RFC4552"/>. Since there is no standard
      defined for native OSPFv2 IPsec, some form of secure tunnel is required
      to provide confidentiality.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This specification defines the Prefix Source Router-ID sub-TLV as
      described in <xref target="section-6"/>. This value should be added to
      the both existing "OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV Sub-TLVs" and "OSPFv3
      Extended-LSA Sub-TLVs" registries.</t>

      <t>The following sub-TLV is added to the "OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV
      Sub-TLVs" registry. The allocation policy is IETF Review as defined in
      <xref target="RFC7684"/></t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Code Point  |   Description         |           Status       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       4        | Prefix Source Sub-TLV |   Allocation from IANA |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
Figure 4:  Code Point in "OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV Sub-TLVs"
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t/>

      <t>The following sub-TLV is added to the "OSPFv3 Extended-LSA Sub-TLVs"
      registry. The allocation policy is IETF Review as defined in <xref
      target="RFC8362"/></t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Code Point  |   Description         |           Status       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       27       | Prefix Source Sub-TLV |   Allocation from IANA |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
Figure 5:  Code Point in "OSPFv3 Extended-LSA Sub-TLVs"
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgement">
      <t>Many thanks to Les Ginsberg for his suggestions on this draft. Also
      thanks to Jeff Tantsura, Rob Shakir, Gunter Van De Velde, Goethals Dirk,
      Shaofu Peng, and John E Drake for their valuable comments.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2328"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4552"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5340"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5709"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7166"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7474"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7684"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7770"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7794"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8362"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8476"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7752"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-ls-segment-routing-ext"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-ospf-mpls-elc" ?>
    </references>

    <section anchor="Appendix-A" title="Inter-Area Topology Retrieval Process">
      <t>When an IP SDN Controller receives BGP-LS <xref target="RFC7752"/>
      information, it should compare the prefix Network Layer Reachability
      Information (NLRI) that is included in the BGP-LS NLRI. When it
      encounters the same prefix but with different source router ID, it
      should extract the corresponding area-ID, rebuild the link between these
      two source routers in the non-backbone area. Below is one example that
      based on the Figure 1:</t>

      <t>Assuming we want to rebuild the connection between router S1 and
      router S2 located in area 1:</t>

      <t><list style="letters">
          <t>Normally, router S1 will advertise prefix N1 within its
          router-LSA.</t>

          <t>When this router-LSA reaches the ABR router R1, it will convert
          it into summary-LSA, add the Prefix Source Router-ID sub-TLV, which
          is router id of S1 in this example.</t>

          <t>R1 then floods this extension summary-LSA to R0, which is using
          the BGP-LS protocol with IP SDN Controller. The controller then
          knows the prefix for N1 is from S1.</t>

          <t>Router S2 will perform a similar process, and the controller will
          also learn that prefix N1 is also from S2.</t>

          <t>Then it can reconstruct the link between S1 and S2, using the
          prefix N1. The topology within Area 1 can then be reconstructed
          accordingly.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Iterating the above process continuously, the IP SDN controller can
      retrieve a detailed topology that spans multiple areas.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Appendix-B"
             title="Special Considerations on Inter-Area Topology Retrieval ">
      <t>The above topology retrieval process can be applied in the case where
      each point-to-point or multi-access link connecting routers is assigned
      a unique prefix. However, there are some situations where this heuristic
      cannot be applied. Specifically, the cases where the link is unnumbered
      or the prefix corresponding to the link is an anycast prefix.</t>

      <t>The <xref target="Appendix-A"/> heuristic to rebuild the topology can
      normally be used if all links are numbered. For anycast prefixes, if it
      corresponds to the loopback interface and has a host prefix length,
      i.e., 32 for IPv4 prefixes and 128 for IPv6 prefixes, <xref
      target="Appendix-A"/> can also applied since these anycast prefixes are
      not required to reconstruct the topology.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
