<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v5 rel. 3 U (http://www.xmlspy.com)
     by Daniel M Kohn (private) -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-lsr-ospf-prefix-originator-03"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="OSPF Prefix Originator">OSPF Extension for Prefix
    Originator</title>

    <author fullname="Aijun Wang" initials="A" surname="Wang">
      <organization>China Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Beiqijia Town, Changping District</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>102209</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>wangaj3@chinatelecom.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Acee Lindem" initials="A" surname="Lindem">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>301 Midenhall Way</street>

          <city>Cary</city>

          <region>NC</region>

          <code>27513</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>acee@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jie Dong" initials="J" surname="Dong">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jie.dong@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Peter Psenak" initials="P" surname="Psenak">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Pribinova Street 10</street>

          <city>Bratislava</city>

          <region>Eurovea Centre, Central 3</region>

          <code>81109</code>

          <country>Slovakia</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>ppsenak@cisco.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ketan Talaulikar" initials="K" surname="Talaulikar">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>S.No. 154/6, Phase I, Hinjawadi</street>

          <city>Pune</city>

          <region/>

          <code>411 057</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ketant@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="27" month="August" year="2019"/>

    <area>RTG Area</area>

    <workgroup>LSR Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>RFC</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes Open Shortest Path First (OSPF) v2 and OSPFv3
      encodings to advertise the router-id of the originator of inter-area
      prefixes for OSPFv2 and OSPFv3 Link-State Advertisement (LSA), which are
      needed in several use cases in multi-area OSPF use cases.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="section-1" title="Introduction">
      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-ospf-mpls-elc"/> defines mechanisms to Entropy
      Readable Label Depth (ERLD) for ingress Label Switching Router (LSR) to
      discover each LSR's capability of performing Entropy Label (EL) -based
      load-balancing in Multi Protocol Label Switch (MPLS) networks. The
      ingress LSR can use this information to push the appropriate label stack
      for specific traffic, especially in segment routing environments and
      other stacked LSPs scenarios.</t>

      <t>However, in inter-area scenarios, the Area Border Router (ABR) does
      not advertise the originating OSPF router-id for inter-area prefixes. An
      OSPF router in one area doesn't know where the prefixes really came from
      and can't determine the router that originated inter-area prefixes and
      then can't judge the ERLD capabilities of the destination. It is
      necessary to transfer the originator information of these inter-area
      prefixes to ensure the ingress LSR constructs the right label stack.</t>

      <t>More generally, <xref target="RFC8476"/> defines a mechanism to
      advertise multiple types of supported Maximum SID Depths (MSD) at node
      and/or link granularity. This information will be referred when the
      head-end router starts to send traffic to destination prefixes. In
      inter-area scenario, it is also necessary for the sender to learn the
      capabilities of the receivers associated with the inter-area
      prefixes.</t>

      <t>There is also another scenario where knowing the originator of
      inter-area prefixes is useful. For example, Border Gateway Protocol
      Link-State (BGP-LS) <xref target="RFC7752"/> describes mechanisms using
      the BGP protocol to advertise Link-State information. This can enable an
      Software Definition Network (SDN) controller to collect the underlay
      network topology automatically.</t>

      <t>But if the underlay network is divided into multiple areas and
      running the OSPF protocol, it is not easy for the SDN controller to
      rebuild the multi-area topology, because normally an ABR that connects
      multiple areas will hide the detailed topology information for these
      non-backbone areas. If only the internal routers within backbone area
      run the BGP-LS protocol, they just learn and report the summary network
      information from the non-backbone areas. If the SDN controller can learn
      the originator of the inter-area prefixes, it is possible to rebuild the
      inter-area topology automatically.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC7794"/> introduces the Intermediate System to
      Intermediate System (IS-IS) &ldquo;IPv4/IPv6 Source Router IDs&rdquo;
      Type-Length-Value (TLV) to advertise the source of the prefixes
      redistributed from a different IS-IS level. This TLV can be used in the
      above scenarios. Such solution can also be applied in networks that run
      the OSPF protocol, but the related LSAs TLV must be extended.</t>

      <t>This draft provides such solution for the OSPFv2 and OSPFv3
      protocols.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Conventions used in this document">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>
      .</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>The following terms are used in this document:<list style="symbols">
          <t>ABR: Area Border Router</t>

          <t>ERLD: Entropy Readable Label Depth</t>

          <t>EL: Entropy Label</t>

          <t>IS-IS: Intermediate System to Intermediate System</t>

          <t>LSA: Link-State Advertisement</t>

          <t>MSD: Maximum SID Depths</t>

          <t>NLRI: Network Layer Reachability Information</t>

          <t>OSPF: Open Shortest Path First</t>

          <t>SID: Segment IDentifier</t>

          <t>SDN: Software Definition Network</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Conventions used in this document">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>
      .</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Scenario Description">
      <t>Figure 1 illustrates the topology scenario when OSPF is running in
      multi-area. R0-R4 are routers in backbone area, S1-S4,T1-T4 are internal
      routers in area 1 and area 2 respectively. R1 and R3 are area border
      routers between area 0 and area 1. R2 and R4 are area border routers
      between area 0 and area 2. N1 is the network between router S1 and S2
      and N2 is the network between router T1 and T2. Ls1 is the loopback
      address of Node S1 and Lt1 is the loopback address of Node T1.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[                     +-----------------+
                     |IP SDN Controller|
                     +--------+--------+
                              |
                              | BGP-LS
                              |
 +---------------------+------+--------+-----+--------------+
 | +--+        +--+   ++-+   ++-+    +-++   + -+        +--+|
 | |S1+--------+S2+---+R1+---|R0+----+R2+---+T1+--------+T2||
 | +-++   N1   +-++   ++-+   +--+    +-++   ++++   N2   +-++|
 |   |           |     |               |     ||           | |
 |   |           |     |               |     ||           | |
 | +-++        +-++   ++-+           +-++   ++++        +-++|
 | |S4+--------+S3+---+R3+-----------+R4+---+T3+--------+T4||
 | +--+        +--+   ++-+           +-++   ++-+        +--+|
 |                     |               |                    |
 |                     |               |                    |
 |         Area 1      |     Area 0    |      Area 2        |
 +---------------------+---------------+--------------------+

       Figure 1: OSPF Inter-Area Prefix Originator Scenario
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>If S1 wants to send traffic to prefix Lt1 that is connected T1 in
      another area, it should know the ERLD, and MSD values that are
      associated with the node T1, and then construct the right label stack at
      the ingress node for the target traffic.</t>

      <t>In another scenario, If R0 has some method to learn the originator of
      network N1 and reports such information to IP SDN controller, then it is
      possible for the controller to retrieval the topology in non-backbone
      area. The topology retrieval process and its usage limitation are
      described in the <xref target="Appendix-A"/> and <xref
      target="Appendix-B"/> .</t>

      <t>From the above scenarios, we can conclude it is useful to introduce
      and define the prefix originator sub TLV within OSPF.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="section-6" title="Prefix Source Router-ID sub-TLV">
      <t><xref target="RFC7684"/> and <xref target="RFC8362"/> define the TLV
      extensions for OSPFv2 and OSPFv3 respectively. These documents
      facilitate addition of new attributes for prefixes. Based on these
      formats, we can define new sub-TLV to advertise the &ldquo;Prefix Source
      Router ID&rdquo;, as that defined in <xref target="RFC7794"/>.</t>

      <t>The &ldquo;Prefix Source Router-ID&rdquo; sub-TLV has the following
      format:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[ 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |               Type            |              Length           |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |                Prefix Source Router-ID                        |
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
        Figure 2: Prefix Source Router-ID sub-TLV Format
   ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Source Router-ID Sub-TLV Type: TBD1<xref target="RFC7684"/> or
          TBD2 <xref target="RFC8362"/></t>

          <t>Length: 4</t>

          <t>Value: Router-ID of OSPFv2/OSPFv3 source router</t>
        </list>For OSPFv2, this sub-TLV is a sub-TLV of OSPFv2 Extended Prefix
      TLV, which SHOULD be included in the &ldquo;OSPFv2 Extended Prefix
      Opaque LSA&rdquo; .</t>

      <t>For OSPFv3, this sub-TLV is a sub-TLV of "Inter-Area-Prefix TLV",
      which SHOULD be included in the "E-Inter-Area-Prefix-LSA".</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Extended LSA Elements of Procedure">
      <t>When an ABR, for example R2 in Figure 1, receives the Router-LSA
      announcement in area 2, it should originate the corresponding
      &ldquo;OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSA&rdquo; for OSPFv2 or
      &ldquo;E-Inter-Area-Prefix-LSA&rdquo; for OSPFv3 that includes the
      Source Router-ID sub-TLV for the network prefixes, e.g., for prefix Lt1,
      N2. etc., which identifies the source router that advertised the
      prefix.</t>

      <t>When S1 in another area receives such LSA, it then can learn that
      prefix Lt1 is associated with node T1, check the ERLD, or MSD value
      according to its necessity, and construct the right label stack at the
      ingress node S1 for the traffic destined to Lt1.</t>

      <t>When R0 receives such LSA, it learns the Prefix Source Router-id and
      includes it in the prefix information advertised to an SDN controller as
      described in<xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-ls-segment-routing-ext">
      </xref>. The SDN controller can then use such information to build the
      inter-area topology according to the process described in the <xref
      target="Appendix-A"/>. The topology retrieval process may not suitable
      for some environments as stated in <xref target="Appendix-B"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Security concerns for OSPF are addressed in <xref
      target="RFC5709"/></t>

      <t>Advertisement of the additional information defined in this document
      introduces no new security concerns</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This specification defines one Prefix Source Router-ID sub-TLV as
      described in <xref target="section-6"/>. This value should be added to
      the existing "OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV Sub-TLVs" registry and "OSPFv3
      Extended-LSA Sub-TLVs registry" respectively.</t>

      <t>The following new sub-TLV is added to the registry of "OSPFv2
      Extended Prefix TLV Sub-TLVs". The allocation policy is IETF Review that
      defined in <xref target="RFC7684"/></t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-++++++++
|    Code Point  |   Description         |           Status            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-++++++++
|       TBD      | Prefix Source Sub-TLV |   Allocation from IANA      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-++++++++
Figure 3:  CodePoint in "OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV Sub-TLVs"
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t/>

      <t>The following new sub-TLV is added to the registry of "OSPFv3
      Extended-LSA Sub-TLVs". The allocation policy is IETF Review that
      defined in <xref target="RFC8362"/></t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-++++++++
|    Code Point  |   Description         |           Status            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-++++++++
|       TBD      | Prefix Source Sub-TLV |   Allocation from IANA      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-++++++++
Figure 4:  CodePoint in "OSPFv3 Extended-LSA Sub-TLVs"
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgement">
      <t>Many thanks to Les Ginsberg for his valuable suggestions on this
      draft. And also thanks Jeff Tantsura,Rob Shakir, Van De Velde Gunter,
      Goethals Dirk, Shaofu Peng, John E Drake for their valuable comments on
      this draft.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5709"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7684"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7752"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7794"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8362"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8476"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-ls-segment-routing-ext"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-ospf-mpls-elc" ?>
    </references>

    <section anchor="Appendix-A" title="Inter-Area Topology Retrieval Process">
      <t>When an IP SDN Controller receives this information, it should
      compare the prefix Network Layer Reachability Information (NLRI) that
      included in the BGP-LS packet. When it encounters the same prefix but
      with different source router ID, it should extract the corresponding
      area-ID, rebuild the link between these two different source routers in
      non-backbone area. Belows is one example that based on the Figure 1:</t>

      <t>Assuming we want to rebuild the connection between router S1 and
      router S2 that locates in area 1:</t>

      <t><list style="letters">
          <t>Normally, router S1 will advertise prefix N1 within its
          router-LSA.</t>

          <t>When this router-LSA reaches the ABR router R1, it will convert
          it into summary-LSA, add the Prefix Source Router-ID sub-TLV, which
          is router id of S1 in this example.</t>

          <t>R1 then floods this extension summary-LSA to R0, which is running
          BGP-LS protocol with IP SDN Controller. The controller then knows
          the prefixes of N1 is from S1.</t>

          <t>Router S2 will do the similar process, and the controller will
          also learn that prefixes N1 is also from S2.</t>

          <t>Then it can reconstruct the link between S1 and S2, using the
          prefix N1. The topology within Area 1 can then be reconstructed
          accordingly.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Iterating the above process continuously, the IP SDN controller can
      retrieve a detailed topology that spans multiple areas.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Appendix-B"
             title="Special Considerations on Inter-Area Topology Retrieval ">
      <t>The above topology retrieval process can be applied in the case where
      each link between routers is assigned a unique prefix. However, there
      are some situations where this heuristic cannot be applied.
      Specifically, the cases where the link is unnumbered or the prefix
      corresponding to the link is an anycast prefix.</t>

      <t>The <xref target="Appendix-A"/> heuristic to rebuild the topology can
      normally be used if all links are numbered. For anycast prefixes, if it
      corresponds to the loopback interface and has a host prefix length,
      i.e., 32 for IPv4 prefixes and 128 for IPv6 prefixes, <xref
      target="Appendix-A"/> can also apply.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
